<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><api:response xmlns:api="http://www.symplectic.co.uk/publications/api"><api:version uri="https://mypublications.shef.ac.uk/" elements-version="6.15.0.3976" schema-version="6.13" product-name="myPublications"/><api:request href="https://mypublications.shef.ac.uk:8091/secure-api/v6.13/users/525"/><api:result><api:object category="user" id="525" proprietary-id="00732114" authenticating-authority="MUSE" username="PR1KLK" last-affected-when="2024-04-19T12:55:30.777+01:00" last-modified-when="2024-03-14T08:27:24.24+00:00" href="https://mypublications.shef.ac.uk:8091/secure-api/v6.13/users/525" created-when="2010-04-15T10:09:00.907+01:00" type-id="1" type-display-name="Person" type="person"><api:privacy-level>Public</api:privacy-level><api:privacy-level-locked>false</api:privacy-level-locked><api:ever-approved>true</api:ever-approved><api:allow-type-switching>true</api:allow-type-switching><api:is-current-staff>true</api:is-current-staff><api:photo href="https://mypublications.shef.ac.uk:8091/secure-api/v6.13/users/525/photo?type=profile" last-modified-when="2023-07-21T16:27:59.513+01:00"/><api:is-academic>true</api:is-academic><api:is-student>false</api:is-student><api:is-login-allowed>true</api:is-login-allowed><api:title>Dr</api:title><api:initials>KL</api:initials><api:last-name>Kuykendall</api:last-name><api:first-name>Kevin</api:first-name><api:email-address>K.L.KUYKENDALL@SHEFFIELD.AC.UK</api:email-address><api:primary-group-descriptor>AAP</api:primary-group-descriptor><api:arrive-date>2004-09-01</api:arrive-date><api:institutional-email-is-public>true</api:institutional-email-is-public><api:claimed>true</api:claimed><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="1" field-name="DATE_OF_BIRTH">12/02/1962</api:organisation-defined-data><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="2" field-name="UOA"/><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="3" field-name="PLANNING_UNIT">FCA</api:organisation-defined-data><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="4" field-name="DEPARTMENT">AAP</api:organisation-defined-data><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="5" field-name="HESA_ID">0411590117180</api:organisation-defined-data><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="6" field-name="RESEARCH_GROUP_1"/><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="7" field-name="RESEARCH_GROUP_2"/><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="8" field-name="RESEARCH_GROUP_3"/><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="9" field-name="RESEARCH_GROUP_4"/><api:organisation-defined-data field-number="10" field-name="PERSONNEL_AREA">ACAD</api:organisation-defined-data><!--Additional generic field values would appear here, but are witheld because your account does not have access to sensitive HR data.--><api:user-search-settings><api:default><api:affiliation>"Sheffield" OR "Witwatersrand"</api:affiliation><api:name>"Kuykendall, K. L." OR "Kuykendall Kevin L" OR "Kuykendall Kevin" OR "Kuykendall K"</api:name><api:start-date>1990-01-01</api:start-date></api:default></api:user-search-settings><api:records><api:record format="native" id="840208" source-id="1" source-name="manual" source-display-name="Manual" id-at-source="C93B7913-7830-4C82-85EC-B0CECD3F0C31" last-modified-when="2023-07-21T16:22:24.92+01:00"><api:native><api:field name="research-interests" type="text" display-name="Research interests"><api:text privacy="public">My current areas of research focus on two topics. First, I am conducting fieldwork in Palaeolithic archaeology at Creswell Crags in Derbyshire, UK. This project has been funded by several university sources and is the focus of an AHRC research grant currently being developed (supported by a FRAF award in Spring 2023). The research project involves a regional landscape archaeology approach to the Creswell Crags gorge and surrounding areas, developing a novel ‘non-cave’ strategy of geophysics/ ground penetrating radar survey and test pit excavations. Our project and this field strategy has been highlighted in the East Midlands 2023 Updated Period Resource Assessment: The Palaeolithic Period (see Section 10). The aim is to recover Palaeolithic archaeology allowing us to refine our understanding of hominin adaptive activities during the extreme climatic conditions during the glacial and interglacial periods between 60-12kya. Our fieldwork for 2023 involves a volunteer cohort from the local Creswell Crags region who will participate in fieldwork and co-produce a range of outputs for future public engagement with heritage issues. As part of this research, I have also been involved as a collaborator with Dr Angharad Jones (Curator at Creswell Crags) in the ongoing process to develop a nomination bid for WHS status, and the research project plays a key role in this process by highlighting the current research potential of the site. This research project has also been identified as a future REF Impact Case Study in the Department of Archaeology. 

Second, I am involved in ongoing research about the evolution of life history in early hominins, following previous publications on this topic (dental development in extant apes; Paranthropus life history). I am currently collaborating with a team led by Gabriele Macho (Oxford) and developing a method to use dental maturity scores (DMS) to compare the patterns of dental maturity as a marker of life history shifts in Australopithecus, Paranthropus and early Homo. We have a collaboration with a number of other researchers for the wider context of the project, involving a reassessment of Plio-Pleistocene hominin diversity using developmental and other traits. So far we have compiled the largest database of extant ape and fossil hominin tooth developmental data, and are building a collaboration to collect a wider range of data from existing CT-based data sets of fossil and extant monkeys and apes. We have presented papers at two international conferences and have 2 papers in progress with potential for additional publications in future. This research is not funded at this time, but the initial papers will be the basis of future funding applications that I will be involved in.</api:text></api:field><api:field name="teaching-summary" type="text" display-name="Teaching summary"><api:text privacy="public">I am heavily involved in UG and PGT teaching in the Department of Archaeology, and have been the programme director of the MSc Palaeoanthropology programme since its inception in 2004. In a typical academic year, I have delivered 5 UG or PGT modules in their entirety, and team-taught on 7 others. I took over as Programme Director of the MSc Archaeological Science programme in 2022. I supervise a varying number of UG and MSc dissertation projects in palaeoanthropology and related topics each year, and I currently supervise 5 PhD students. 

I have developed the MSc Palaeoanthropology Course since 2004, introducing new modules in human evolutionary theory (AAP6154) and practical work using our hominin fossil cast collection (AAP693). In response to the Covid pandemic I made substantial modifications to enhance the delivery of laboratory practicals using online resources and data sources, most of which have been retained due to their added value. I have also been involved in the curriculum developments for new modules in human evolution (AAP118, AAP21003) that form the core of UG teaching at L1 and L2. I have also worked over the past several years to develop the Digital Cultural Heritage module (AAP6219) to support the department’s Heritage-based programmes, but it is also available as a general option to all PGT students. This module has become one of the more popular modules on offer, currently attracting over 50 students per term. 
I was on a period of Study Leave in Fall Term 2022, and in the Spring 2023 I had a reduced teaching load due to a FRAF award and as a result of closed UG recruitment in light of the upcoming department closure. 

Current Teaching (Spring 2023): 

Course Title                                                                    Level of Teaching	                                                 Student Contact Hours
MSc Palaeaoanthropology	                                        PGT course coordinator (since 2004)	                 1 P/T student (2023 enrolment) 
MSc Archaeological Science	                                PGT course coordinator (since Spring 2022)	 1 student (2023 enrolment)
AAP6154 Human Evolution: Theory and Practice 	PGT module coordinator/ lecturer	                 24 hrs (2 students 2023)
AAP693 Evolutionary Anatomy 	                                PGT Module coordinator/ lecturer	                 30 hrs (did not run 2023)
AAP641 Research Design in Anthropology	                PGT lecturer/ Seminar leader	                        8 hrs (10 students 2023)
AAP6144 Quantitative Methods in Anthropology 	PGT Module coordinator/ lecturer               	22 hrs (12 students 2023)
AAP6898 Dissertation (Year)	                               MSc Supervisor (Palaeoanthropology)         	Individual supervision of dissertation 
AAP6219 Digital Cultural Heritage 	                       PGT ‘guest’ lecturer	                                        2 hrs (1 lecture; 51 students 2023)
AAP21003 Primate and human evolution 	               UG Module coordinator/ lecturer 	                       20 hrs (4 students 2023)</api:text></api:field></api:native></api:record></api:records><api:fields/><api:relationships href="https://mypublications.shef.ac.uk:8091/secure-api/v6.13/users/525/relationships"/><api:user-identifier-associations user-id="525" proprietary-id="00732114" username="PR1KLK"><api:user-identifier-association scheme="email-address" status="claimed" decision="always-me">K.L.KUYKENDALL@SHEFFIELD.AC.UK</api:user-identifier-association><api:user-identifier-association scheme="figshare-for-institutions-user-account-id" status="claimed" decision="always-me">00732114</api:user-identifier-association><api:user-identifier-association scheme="orcid" status="claimed" decision="always-me">0000-0001-8284-2735</api:user-identifier-association><api:user-identifier-association scheme="scopus-author-id" status="claimed" decision="always-me">6602857490</api:user-identifier-association><api:user-identifier-association scheme="figshare-for-institutions-user-id" status="claimed" decision="always-me">2747923</api:user-identifier-association></api:user-identifier-associations></api:object></api:result></api:response>